{"tossups": [{"question": "A paper by Donald Regan interprets the result of this court case to hold that people cannot be forced to become Good Samaritans. Justice Byron White claimed that the result of this case was the only irredeemable error the court made during his tenure. The<em> Casey</em> case built upon the result of this case to expand the definition of the word \u201cviability,\u201d doing away with its trimester-based framework. For ten points, name this 1973 case that legalized abortion in the U.S.", "answer": "<b> Roe</b> v.<b> Wade</b> (accept either underlined portion; accept in either order)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Before this battle, Thomas Rusk was told to take control if another commander refused to fight. The\u201cTwin Sister\u201d cannons were smuggled down the Mississippi River in preparation for this battle. Manuel Castrillon\u2019s sleeping troops were ambushed in this battle, in which the victorious side rallied with cries to\u201cremember the Alamo.\u201d During this 18-minute engagement, the troops of Sam Houston captured Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna. For ten points, name this battle that secured Texan independence from Mexico.", "answer": "Battle of<b> San Jacinto</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "On this island, the ambush of the Four Four Bravo patrol prompted racial violence during Black July. Lourenco de Almeida established a Portuguese fort on this island to counter Jaffna influence. Thanks to the evangelizing of Mahinda, Ashoka\u2019s son, Theravada Buddhism is prominent on this island, contrary to the neighboring mainland. For ten points, name this home island of the Sinhalese and Tamil ethnic groups, a country whose largest city is Colombo.", "answer": "<b> Sri Lanka</b> (accept<b> Ceylon</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this general term for intentional violence committed to achieve a political or ideological goal.", "answer": "<b> terrorism</b> (accept word forms; prompt on close, descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "Henry le Despenser ended this conflict with a victory at North Walsham. A leader of this event was slain while meeting with William Walworth at Smithfield. The Savoy Palace was burned down during this event, in which Simon Sudbury was killed after the cleric John Ball incited protesters to storm the Tower of London. This event was prompted by a poll tax of Richard II. Wat Tyler led, for ten points, what 1381 rebellion of the lower class in England?", "answer": "<b> Peasant</b>\u2019s Revolt (or uprising, etc.; accept<b> Wat Tyler\u2019s</b> Rebellion, Revolt, etc. before his name is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this location, soapstone monoliths depict raptor-like \u201cbirds of heaven,\u201d and houses in this site are made of mud bricks called daga. This city is legendarily conflated with the Palace of the Queen of Sheba. Decorative masonry used in a Conical Tower in this city lead to its Shona name meaning \u201chouses of stone,\u201d and parallel walls surrounding this city are known as the Great Enclosure. For ten points, name this \u201cGreat\u201d city, built several centuries ago in Masvingo Province in its namesake African country.", "answer": "Great<b> Zimbabwe</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Louis-Antoine Beaunier received a royal commission to construct one of these structures to aid the mining industry in the Loire basin. The first of these structures in Paris started at the Gare du Nord. Saint-\u00b4Etienne was an early center for these structures, which were financed by the Perri`ere brothers through the Cr\u00b4edit Mobilier. In 1937, these systems were nationalized in France under the SNCF, which still runs them today. For ten points, name these structures, which link cities like Lyon and Paris.", "answer": "French<b> railways</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The Sanskrit word<em> preta</em> describes supernatural beings that underwent this process and became chronically hungry. Buddhist scholars have debated whether<em> bardo</em> takes place during this process, an idea recorded in the Tibetan Book of the Dead, since shortly after the death of the Buddha. A soul that has achieved<em> moksha</em> has been liberated from<em> samsara</em>, the eternal cycle of this process. For ten points, name this process that, in Jainism, Buddhism, and Hinduism, occurs after death.", "answer": "<b> reincarnation</b> (or<b> rebirth</b>; accept<b> transmigration</b> of the soul; accept<b> punarjanman</b>; accept<b> samsara</b> before mentioned; prompt on descriptions of birth and/or death)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man constructed, and named for himself, a fortified road along the Arabian border. The Edict on Maximum Prices was this ruler\u2019s attempt to combat inflation by replacing the debased<em> denarius</em>. He appointed his valuable ally, the general Maximian, as co-ruler with Galerius and Chlorus as junior rulers. This man\u2019s ascension ended the Crisis of the Third Century and, he ordered the last major persecution of Christians in his empire. For ten points, name this Roman Emperor whose tetrarchy split the empire into four sections.", "answer": "<b> Diocletian</b> (or<b> Diocles</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this populist Louisiana governor, nicknamed the \u201cKingfish,\u201d who promoted the \u201cShare Our Wealth\u201d program.", "answer": "Huey P.<b> Long</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Two answers required. A source of tension between these two countries was one\u2019s use of the phrase\u201clegitimate grievance\u201d to describe the Chushi Gangdruk uprising in the other. These two countries fought a border war over the Ussuri River. One of these two countries provided half of the investment for the other\u2019s first Five Year Plan. Richard Nixon visited one of these two countries in 1972 in part because of its rivalry with the other. For ten points, name these countries which \u201csplit\u201d in the early 1960s, despite being the two largest Communist countries in the world.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> and the<b> Soviet Union</b> (accept<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b> or<b> USSR</b> or<b> CCCP</b> or<b> SSSR</b> for \u201cSoviet Union;\u201d accept<b> Zhonghua Renmin Gongheguo </b>or<b> Zhongguo</b> for \u201cChina;\u201d accept descriptions of the<b> Sino-Soviet</b> Split)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s grandsons included Julian, an accomplished biologist in his own right.", "answer": "Thomas Henry<b> Huxley</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one role, this actor is shot many times before falling face-first onto a cake, walking into a bear trap, and falling off of a boat. This man, who played Officer Nordberg in the</b> <em><b>Naked Gun</b></em><b> films, won the 1968 Heisman trophy while playing for (+)</b> <b>USC and became</b> <b>the first player to rush for 2,000 yards in an NFL season. A In 1994, this man hired Robert Kardashian and Johnnie Cochran as (*) </b> defense attorneys. The book<em> If I Did It</em> was supposedly written by, for ten points, what running back who was acquitted of murdering Ron Goldman and his ex-wife, Nicole Brown?", "answer": "Orenthal James \u201cOJ\u201d<b> Simpson</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>An invasion of this country was justified through Article IV of the Treaty of Guarantee. Voters from this country repeatedly rejected the Annan Plans of reunification. Nikos Sampson was placed in power in this country by the EOKA attempting to fulfill the idea</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>enosis. Operation Attila was an attack on this country following the overthrow</b> <b>enosis. Operation Attila was an attack on this country following the overthrow</b> <b>of Archbishop Makarios, and fighting in this country led to the creation of the (*)</b> <b>of Archbishop Makarios, and fighting in this country led to the creation of the (*)</b> Green Line and a UN buffer zone. For ten points, name this Mediterranean island country divided into zones dominated by Greek and Turkish partisans.", "answer": "<b> Cyprus</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Gustavus Fox\u2019s attempt to relieve this location failed when the</b><em><b> Powhatan</b></em><b> was sent to Florida without his knowledge. Abner Doubleday ordered a cannon salvo on Cummings Point to defend this location. The unarmed (+)</b><em><b> Star of the West</b></em><b> was sent to resupply this location but was promptly fired upon. PGT Beauregard\u2019s bombardment of this location began when Robert Anderson\u2019s (*) </b> Union troops refused to vacate their defenses in Charleston harbor. For ten points, name this South Carolina fort whose seizure in 1861 marked the beginning of the Civil War.", "answer": "Fort<b> Sumter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this Ba\u2019ath Party leader who was hanged in December 2006 for crimes against humanity carried out as President of Iraq.", "answer": "Saddam<b> Hussein</b> (prompt on Saddam alone)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>A crime is committed on this holiday in the Hercule Poirot story \u201cMurder in the Mews.\u201dThe namesake of this holiday is idolized as a distant ancestor of the central family of the novel</b><em><b> Martin Chuzzlewit</b></em><b>. (+) Evey [ee-vee] Hammond is saved from assault on this holiday in a graphic novel by Alan Moore; a year later, she sets a subway train full of explosives to blow up a government building. The title character of (*) </b> <em>V for Vendetta</em> wears a mask representing the namesake of, for ten points, what British holiday, the subject of the rhyme \u201cRemember, remember, the fifth of November?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Guy Fawkes</b> Day and/or Night (accept the<b> Fifth of November</b> until read; prompt on descriptions of Gunpowder (Plot) Day, Bonfire Day, and/or Firework Day)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}